<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ed Prince</title>
    <description>Balancing a life of technology and climbing.
</description>
    <link>http://edwardprince.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://edwardprince.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 04:45:16 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 04:45:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alpine Adventures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/group.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Group photo on the Grand Montets Ridge&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Stood at the top of the Grand Montets Ridge, just below the lift station platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summer saw me take the plunge for a three week excursion to Chamonix, from 24th June to the 16th July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;petite-verte&quot;&gt;Petite Verte&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first route we attempted was one I had heard about from friends who had completed it whilst on Alpine
training courses - so it seemed an appropriate place to dip our feet back into the Alps. Gearing up for the
first time that trip was as exhilerating as ever, and the short, easy approach to the bergschrund flew by -
culminating with breathtaking snippets of views over to &lt;em&gt;Les Drus&lt;/em&gt; through gaps in the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After hitting the Bergschrund, the guidebook suggested a snow slope up to the crest of the ridge, however
a bout of hot weather had turned the slope into an ice pitch. Climbing up with a single mountaineering axe
was weird for such a pitch - but nevertheless we made it up safely. The ridge was gorgeous, straightforward
scrambling, with some minor climbing pitches - but nothing tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it to a small overhang of rock whilst we waited for the team in front to move on. An hour and a half
later, after finding it would be sketchy to cross over them, and they were held up by a team retreating down
the ice field in front of them, and the ever-darkening clouds, we decided to call it a day, and headed back
along the ridge to abseil off. By this time, we were abbing into nothingess, and although a shame to retreat
on the first route - a good day had by all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/abseil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abseiling into the abyss&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me abseiling down the ice field towards the bergschrund&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cosmiques-arete&quot;&gt;Cosmiques Arete&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well before heading out to Chamonix, we had decided that Cosmiques must be on the list - so a couple of days
after our attempt on the Petite Verte, we stormed towards the famous arete. After the blistering heat, two
days of storm had arrived, cooling the valley and mountains down substantially, and depositing a fresh batch
of snow on the route. This made for an even more picturesque ascent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cosmiques.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cosmiques Arete&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Naoise Gloser towards the beginning of the route&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the addition of drilled crampon pockets, the “crux” wall was by no means the trickiest section of the
route, instead some of the scrambly sections that were simply covered in snow proved to be more
challenging. I could see quickly why this route was a classic. A short walk from the cable car, a fabulous
approach, a dramatic, yet not technically difficult, exposed ascent, and a grand finale up onto the Midi
station platform - greeted with applause, photos and very excited tourists. Nearly as excited as us to
be there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dent-du-geant&quot;&gt;Dent du Geant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back in January 2016, a friend of mine approached me and a friend with the idea of climbing a huge
spike of rock sticking above the other peaks - at a staggering 4013m. Needless to say, we were taken
with the idea almost instantly. The spike of rock is more commonly known as the Dent du Geant, or
Giants Tooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give ourselves the best shot we could, we took the panoramic lift over the afternoon before, and
set up a bivvy just below the first couloir. We then settled down to the most stunning sunset I have
ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset from the Dent&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sun dipping behind the Aiguille du Midi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/summit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Summit of the Dent&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Stood on the summit at midday&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 16:00:02 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://edwardprince.com/climbing/2017/07/26/alpine-adventures.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://edwardprince.com/climbing/2017/07/26/alpine-adventures.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>climbing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;Tom&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &#39;Hi, Tom&#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 16:00:02 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://edwardprince.com/jekyll/update/2017/07/17/welcome-to-jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://edwardprince.com/jekyll/update/2017/07/17/welcome-to-jekyll.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
